Finding aid for the Elaine Mikels papers, 1967-2004 LSC.1954
UCLA Library Special Collections
Elaine Mikels papers
1969-2004
UCLA Library Special Collections
Mikels, Elaine
LSC.1954
1.6 linear feet (4 document boxes)
Born in Los Angeles in 1921, Elaine Mikels spent her early life in California attending UCLA, UC Berkeley, and USC, later receiving a Master's in Social Work. During this time, Mikels' struggles with expressing and living out her lesbian identity began as she grappled with forming healthy relationships and finding queer community amid the conformist atmosphere of the 1940s, 1950s, and early 1960s. Documented by over two-hundred photographs in the collection, Mikel's political activism on a national scale began in the late 1960s and continued throughout her life as she organized demonstrations for the anti-war movement, created lesbian-feminist communities, and participated in pacifist and civil disobedience actions. The collection includes materials related to the publication of Elaine Mikels' autobiography, as well as a copy of the final published version. Also included are personal papers, journals, correspondence, and various personal materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9969568603606533
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Provenance unknown.
This collection is part of an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW) and the UCLA Library.
Biography
Elaine Mikels was born in 1921 in Los Angeles, and she spent much of her early life in California. Although raised Jewish, she attended Flintridge, a Catholic boarding school. As a closested lesbian, Mikels spoke about her early relationships with women who identified as straight and later went on to get married. Similarly to other closeted women living in the 1940s, she had little concept of how to deal with her own relationships much less build community though shared interests. During this period she suffered from depression and was hospitalized.
After WWII, Mikels worked in Germany with the Quakers through the State Department. She was expelled from the program because of her psychiatric records naming her as a lesbian. She returned to the United States and settled briefly in New York, later traveling for the next several years throughout Europe and the Middle East. In 1951 she settled in San Francisco and pursued social work.
In San Francisco, she became active in the Mattachine Society and ONE magazine. It was also during this period, in 1959, that she established the Conard House. The Conard House was the first halfway house in San Francisco, specifically conceived as a transitional community for people with mental illness who were returning to San Francisco from Napa State Hospital.
Beginning in the late 1960s, Elaine Mikels underwent a period of politicization, "when I broke away from the system. I went through an amazing personal transformation, not unlike many others during this time of civil strife and the war in Vietnam. I was no longer afraid of authority figures." Afterwards, Mikels left her professional social work career for full-time activism. During the 1970s and 1980s, Mikels help found lesbian-feminist communities, organized demonstrations for the anti-war movement, participated in peace actions and walks, and documented lesbian events across the nation. Later in life, Mikels' activism shifted focus to highlight the accomplishments and stories of older women through creating networks such as the Older Lesbians Organizing for Change and publications such as the Older Women's Network. These organizations brought together older feminists and lesbian women who share resources and support for activist goals, housing, employment, and networks of care. In the early 1990s, Mikels wrote the autobiography Just Lucky I Guess: From Closet Lesbian to Radical Dyke which documents her life's struggles, accomplishments, relationships, and global travels.
Chronology
Missing Title
1921 Elaine Mikels born
1951 Elaine Mikels moves to San Francisco
1959 Elaine Mikels founds Conard House
1976 Founding of OWN (Older Women's Network)
1977 Women's Gathering in Ashland, OR.
1981 Women's Pentagon Action
June 12, 1982 Nuclear Disarmament Rally
June 3 - July 4, 1983 PeaceWalk from Durham, N.C. to Seneca Peace Camp
1983 Dyke Olympics
1984 PeaceWalk from Gainesville, FL to Key West, FL.
Scope and Content
The Elaine Mikels papers are comprised of photographs taken by Elaine Mikels in several different locations and with different groups of people. Included are photographs of lesbian activist gatherings, lesbian social gatherings and sports clubs, lesbian writing groups, and self-published newsletters. The collection also includes materials related to the publication of Elaine Mikels' autobiography, Just Lucky I Guess: From Closet Lesbian to Radical Dyke, as well as a copy of the final published version. Also included are personal papers, journals, correspondence, and various personal materials. The pictures contained in the Mikels collection of Feminary writers, producers, and supporters reflect a new political imperative in Mikel's work. The most prominent participant in the Feminary editorial collective was Minnie Bruce Pratt; photographs of her are contained within the collection. Also represented in the collection are photographs documenting the Women's Pentagon Action, a two-thousand-woman protest that surrounded the Pentagon in 1981. Eventually, Mikels settled in Santa Fe, but most of her photographic collection represents her time in Oregon and North Carolina.
Organization and Arrangement
Photographs arranged in chronological order are first in the collection. Thereafter, materials are arranged chronologically with the exception of materials about Just Lucky I Guess that, as a continuous project, are kept together.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Elaine Mikels papers (14 items).
Related Materials
Old Lesbians Organizing for Change records (Collection 2203). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA. Papers of Cynthia Rich and Barbara Macdonald Available at Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass. Papers of Barbara Deming Available at Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
Photographs.; Social workers -- California -- San Francisco.; Older lesbians -- United States -- Archives.; Lesbian activists -- United States -- Archives.; June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives; June L. Mazer Lesbian Archive at UCLA; Mikels, Elaine
- Older Women's Network (OWN), 1976 - 1982; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  45 Miscellaneous photos of the Older Women's Network (OWN). Also includes a note from Elaine Mikels concerning the founding of OWN.
- Women's Gathering, 1977; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 2)
  7 photos of the Women's Gathering in Ashland, OR.
- Carpentry Collective, 1978-1980; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 3)
  17 photographs of the women's carpentry collective in Eugene, OR, with some annotations.
- Softball League, 1978-1980; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 4)
  36 photos of the Carpentry Collective's softball league, in game and out.
- Eugene, Oregon, 1978-1980; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 5)
  26 photographs from Mikels' time in Eugene, Oregon.
- Feminary, 1981-1984; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 6)
  57 photographs of fundrasing activities, a costume party, candid group photos, and promotional photos for the publication Feminary.
- Protests, 1981-1982; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 7)
  5 photographs of protesters outside of the trial of the men accused of killing Ronald "Sonny" Antonevitch, Durham, N.C., 1981 April 17. 4 photographs of a rally in support of the Equal Rights Amendment, Raleigh, N.C.
- Women's Pentagon Action, 1981; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 8)
  35 photos of the Women's Pentagon Action.
- Nuclear Disarmament Rally, 1982 June 14; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 9)
  11 photos of the Nuclear Disarmament Rally in Central Park in New York, New York.
- Peace Walk: Durham, North Carolina to Seneca Peace Camp, 1983 June 3 - July 4; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 10)
  5 photographs of the Peace Walk from Durham, N.C. to Seneca Peace Camp. Organized by Elaine Mikels and Mandy Carter.
- Dyke Olympics, 1983; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 11)
  55 photos of the Dyke Olympics outside of Chapel Hill, North Carolina. One-day, one-time event on a woman's land, lesbians only.
- Peace Walk: Gainsville, Florida to Key West, Florida, 1984; photographs of varying size (Box 1, Folder 12)
  53 photos of the Peace Walk from Gainesville, FL to Key West, FL.
- Note to Degania and photographs, circa 1984 - 1993; photographs of varying size, notes, cards (Box 1, Folder 13)
  1 note by Elaine Mikels to Degania detailing her intentions to donate materials to the archive, 27 photos, one flyer, and one card.
- Published Photos, 1969-1991; photos, photocopies (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Contains clippings, photos taken by Elaine Mikels, duplicate prints, publications in which her work was featured, and mock-ups.
- Personal notes, circa 1977 - 1992; handwritten and printed notes (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Personal notes about various subjects such as conferences, poetry, and gay pride.
- Our OWN, 1977 October - 1981 Summer; stapled, photocopied pamphlets (Box 2, Folder 1)
  21 issues of the newsletter Our OWN, the newsletter for the Older Women's Network.
- Published Materials: Lesbians in the Media, 1981-1999; newsprint, printed paper, photocopies, magazine (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Various articles about lesbians in popular culture, the legal system, politics and activist communities.
- Journals, 1984 Christmas - 1988 September 7; bound jounral (Box 2, Folder 3-6)
  Elaine Mikels' personal journals, given as a gift to "Elana." Mikels was sometimes known as "Elana" and "Elana Freedom." Six journals included.
- Assorted programming materials, circa 1987 August - 1999 Summer; printed paper, photocopies, clippings (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Assorted flyers, brochures, postcards, and programming materials.
- Address books, circa 1989 - 1995; four bound address books (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Four bound, differently sized address books containing personal, professional, and activist contacts.
- Correspondence: Publishers, 1989 March 8 - 1993 March 2; typewritten letters (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Letters from and to publishers concerning the publication of Just Lucky I Guess, Elaine's autobiography.
- Profiles and Coverage of Elaine, 1989 May - 1999; newspaper clippings (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Profiles and articles about Elaine Mikels, mostly focused on her lifelong activism.
- Correspondence: Elaine and Jean, 1990 October 30 - 1993 November 7; typewritten letters, handwritten letters (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Correspondence between Elaine and her good friend Jean.
- Sonia Johnson materials, 1991 August 10 - 1994 February; printed paper, photocopies (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Materials related to Reactionary Lesbianism theorist Sonia Johnson, including editorials, opinion pieces, promotional materials.
- Just Lucky I Guess: Notes and drafts, circa 1984 - 1993; handwritten notes, printed paper (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  Notes and drafts of Just Lucky I Guess, Elaine Mikels's autobiography.
- Just Lucky I Guess: Production, 1991 August - 1994 March 22; receipts, printed paper (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  Documentation regarding the production of Just Lucky I Guess. The first folder contains printing and binding costs and receipts while the second folder contains distribution information.
- Just Lucky I Guess: Copyright information, 1993 April - 1994 March; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Documents related to copyright and attributions related to Just Lucky I Guess.
- Just Lucky I Guess: Published copy, 1993; bound book (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Final published, bound copy of Just Lucky I Guess.
- Just Lucky I Guess: Book reviews, 1993 March 2 - 1995 May; printed paper, photocopies, clippings (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Reviews of Just Lucky I Guess from various publications.
- Just Lucky I Guess: Promotional materials, 1993 March 2 - 1994 March; printed paper, flyers (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Promotional materials for the book Just Lucky I Guess, including materials related to readings and signings.
- Just Lucky I Guess: Manuscript, undated; bound printed paper with handwritten notes (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Manuscript and acknowledgements page of Just Lucky I Guess.
- Submissions, circa 1992 - 1994; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Materials submitted to different journals and newspapers for publication.
- Workshop materials, circa 1993 - 2001; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Questionnaires, articles, exercises designed for meditation, and materials on self-help workshops.
- Journal: Costa Rica, 1995 March - April; individual handwritten sheets of paper, envelope (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Personal journal documenting Elaine Mikels' travels in Costa Rica and photocopy of the envelope in which it was contained.
- Clippings, circa 1995 September - 1997 July; newsprint, photocopies, printed paper (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Clippings of Elaine Mikels' editorials, articles, and other writings.
- Unitarian Universalist Congregation of Santa Fe, New Mexico, 2000-2002; printed paper, flyers, bound directories (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Church directories, programs and other information for the Unitarian Universalist Congregation of Santa Fe, New Mexico, of which Elaine Mikels was a member.
- Obituaries, 2004 February - March (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Scope and Content
  Programs for the funeral services for Elaine Mikels and Selma Mikels Lofgren.